# Thomas McMaster BSc (Hons) C.V.

# Data and Database Development.

#### **Contact Information:**

Email: <u>tommcmaster@protonmail.com</u>

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/thomasmcmastersql/

Portfolio: <a href="https://thomas-mcmaster.github.io/">https://thomas-mcmaster.github.io/</a>

#### **Personal Statement:**

I am an IT professional who specializes in relational database development, administration and ETL. My main skills are in SQL Server (2008 R2 to 2019) and automation using Microsoft PowerShell. Since 2004, I have built up a wealth of experience in roles in the public, private and charitable sectors. In each of those roles, I have produced high quality work against deadlines that has helped organisations and colleagues improve their IT processes. I have continued to expand my knowledge and skills into Cloud computing and architecture.

# **Personal Attributes:**

- Punctual, dependable and highly reliable.
- Efficient, highly organized and able to meet deadlines.
- Able to work effectively as part of a team or as an individual with my own sense of motivation.
- Excellent face-to-face and written customer support skills.

#### **Professional Qualifications:**

• Microsoft Certified in Azure Fundamentals (AZ-900).

#### **Professional Experience:**

## March 2022 - present

**Data Engineer - Hymans Robertson** 

Technologies: SQL Server 2008 R2 to 2019, PowerShell, SSIS, SSRS, Azure Dev Ops, Data Factory, Synapse Analytics, Kimball Data Warehousing Concepts, Yaml, Bicep

- Analysis and delivery of changes to SQL-based data for pension scheme administration.
- Introducing Cloud technologies via 'proof-of-concept' projects for Azure Data Factory / Synapse Analytics.
- Online resources managed via CI and CD YAML-based pipelines and Bicep.
- Engineering with Powershell to automate the transfer and anonymisation of data between environments.
- Delivery of solutions and collaboration with colleagues via Git and Azure Dev Ops (ADO).
- Involvement in important finance industry projects including the UK government's Pensions Dashboard and making pension scheme data securely available online.

# September 2020 - March 2022

Senior Data and Integration Officer - East Renfrewshire Council.

Technologies: SQL Server 2008 R2 to 2019, Oracle 12 to 19c, Powershell, SSIS, SSRS, Git, RMAN.

- Council DBA with responsibility for the Authority's SQL Server and Oracle database estate.
- Automation of data transfers with scripted WinSCP.
- Delivery of new reporting suite to monitor health of the Council's database estate.
- Delivery of Git source control for DBA team projects and code.
- Working with suppliers and third parties to ensure smooth on-premise and on-premise-to-cloud migrations.
- Introduction of nightly Oracle 'hot' backup solution to increase service availability.
- Creation of SQL Server corruption checker. Nightly check of 450 SQL databases for new DR strategy.
- Maintenance of Civica Icon and Servitor, NEC's Revenue's and Benefits, NEC Ohms and Tribal's K2.
- Ongoing review of database security, roles and the planned release of encryption-at-rest for SQL Server.

#### February 2019 – September 2020

Database Developer and BI Analyst - Maggie's Centres.

Technologies: SQL Server (2008 R2 to 2017), thankQ CRM, SSIS, SSRS, VBA, Microsoft Office

Automation of IT processes (financial pipelines, stewardship communications, ETL and event promotion).
Monitoring and resolving database performance issues, backup strategy and scheduled maintenance.
Requirements analysis with support staff, colleagues at 26 NHS hospitals and senior stakeholders.
Processing of requests sent to the Database Service Team's inbox.

## June 2011 - February 2019

Systems Analyst / Programmer / Team DBA – Hymans Robertson

Technologies: SQL Server 2008 R2 to 2016, T-SQL, SSIS, MS Access, VBA, SSRS, Civica UPM2 and W2.

- Working in the Third Party Administration Practice as part of the Technical Development Team.
- KPI and SLA reporting to Management.
- Application support for the UPM2 pension management system and its underlying SQL Server databases.
- Trouble-shooting and root cause analysis of Helpdesk System Support requests submitted by end users.
- Communication with stakeholders to identify issues, gather requirements and produce specifications.
- Lead analyst on Practice projects for high profile clients.
- Business process and work flow analysis.
- Team DBA role to maintain and update UPM2 and its associated SQL Server instances.
- Guiding junior analysts and developers.

# June 2010 – June 2011

**Database Programmer – Hewlett Packard** 

Technologies: SQL Server 2008 R2, SSRS, VBA, Microsoft Office

- Working with EMEA Software team to develop relational database systems for use in sales reporting.
- Development, set up and enhancement of relational databases using T-SQL, SSIS and Microsoft Access.
- Analysis and development of existing business processes for conversion to relational databases.

# March 2007 - June 2010

Asset and Systems Support Officer – East Ayrshire Council Roads and Transportation Service Technologies: SQL Server 2000 to 2008 R2, Microsoft Office with VBA, Classic ASP.

- Service contact for all IT requests, trouble-shooting and application support.
- Analysis and development of bespoke database applications for use by Roads Service staff.
- Administrator of GGP Gazetteer software.
- Maintenance of the authority's street gazetteer and associated data to BS7666 standard.
- Secretary of the Scottish Gazetteer Group.

### June 2005 - March 2007

I.T. Technician - Booth Welsh Automation Ltd

Technologies: Microsoft Office with VBA.

- Responsible for IT system and application support across three sites.
- Working with end users across the business to assist with hardware and application issues.
- Development of relational database applications for all departments in the company.
- Support and enhancement of Pegasus accounting software.

# **June 2004 – June 2005**

Systems Analyst (Contracting) – GlaxoSmithKline

Technologies: Microsoft Office with VBA, AspenTech process engineering tools.

• Development of Microsoft Excel and VBA tools to interact with the process engineering software.

## **Education:**

#### 1999-2003:

• Honours Degree (2:1) in Computer Studies from Glasgow Caledonian University.